I've been using the new Chat GPT-5 for the last few days.
This will start today to become your default Chat GPT from now on.
Even if you're a free user.
So, how is it better?
Well, the first thing you'll probably notice is speed.
So this laptop has the previous model, GPT-4 O loaded up.
This has GPT-5.
How many rings does Saturn have?
Go!
Oh my god.
GPT-5 took 3.1 seconds.
This took 6.5.
How many distinct iPhones has Apple made?
Go!
Oh goodness.
Okay.
8.3 seconds, 11.2 seconds.
How many possible type combinations exist in Pokemon?
Not far off.
Actually, quite far off.
This has massively overcomplicated it.
Five seconds, 11 seconds.
So really, when you're asking light questions like this, GPT-5 is between 30 to 50% faster
than the old model.
But I wouldn't really say that speed was one of the key issues before.
There's actually a much more important change happening this generation.
So if you're a really big user of Chat GPT and you're paying the monthly subscription,
it's actually been really freaking confusing to use.
Because you open up the app and you have options.
You can either pick GPT-4 O, O3, O3 Pro, O4 Mini, O4 Mini High, and each one of these
models is its own AI that you can talk to.
And each one is slightly better than the others at one thing or another.
And there's even more than those when you click here to expand.
How on Earth is any normal consumer supposed to be able to decide which one to use for
which question?
I have always wondered.
If this AI is actually smart enough to be in the top 10% of test takers sitting the most
rolling exams on the planet, why can't it also just know what's the best model for
your specific question and make the choice for you?
Well now, finally, GPT-5 can.
This model effectively brings together all the different capabilities of the previously
separated specialized models into one general model.
Which means, if you ask it a question that requires no thinking, then as we've seen it
will use a very light model that's going to be even faster than the old one.
But it also means that if you then ask a heavier question that would benefit from more
thinking, it can now do that thinking without you needing to specifically select a
mode designed for it.
So let's try something very complex.
Make me a game of Tetris that I can play in Canvas.
This is going to mean I can actually play it on the app.
So, I'm doing this first on the old Chat GPT-4O.
This is the best model that you'd have had access to before without paying.
Still though, easily one of the coolest use cases of an AI, we're approaching 200 lines
of code here.
And okay, that took 57 seconds.
And okay, it's very simple.
This is like the most basic possible form of Tetris, but I suppose at the same time I
have just entered one sentence and generated a game.
So now, I want to try the exact same thing, but using O4 Mini-Hi.
So this in the previous generation is the model that would have been specifically recommended
to you for coding.
And you can only get this by paying the monthly subscription.
Go.
Oh, Blum and L, this is significantly faster.
It's done already.
What?
So it was 14 seconds, and the game is actually almost identical to what Chat GPT-4O produced,
just in quarter of the time.
Okay, let's try it on five.
And the thing that I'm curious to see here is, A, does it decide that this is something
that would benefit from more thinking time and take longer, and if it does, does it then
make it better?
Go.
I'd say it's coding slower than O4 Mini-Hi, but still faster than 4/0.
Okay, that was actually pretty fast too.
14 seconds, interestingly, more lines of code than both of them.
So it seems like it is making a more complex game.
That is, like, worlds apart.
So it's the same game, but the pieces now have divides in them.
It's giving me a score.
It's giving me a level.
It's showing me the upcoming piece.
There's controls at the bottom.
Like, okay, don't know me wrong.
None of this is something that you couldn't have achieved using previous Chat GPT models,
but it's just the fact that it had the intuition to bake it all in completely unprompted that's
quite impressive.
Yeah, that's a vastly better game of Tetris.
While we're here, though, let's just do something crazy.
So using O4 Mini-Hi, make me a playable game of chess where the pieces are all Pokemon
with sprites from the internet and make it look premium so that the sprites fill up the
squares.
Go.
Err, an error occurred while trying to run your game.
It's very cool that you can ask it to fix its own bugs, but in my experience, there's
a fairly low success rate and...inter.
Loading this time?
Error again.
Come on.
Third time bucket.
Ah, yes, finally.
It doesn't look terrible.
I mean, it has gone out and picked up Pokemon images from the very first games in the 90s.
And also, it doesn't work.
It's giving me an error message every single time I touch a piece.
Same thing in GPT-5.
Go.
Ah, I rate that.
You see, it specifically said, thinking longer for a better answer.
And thinking longer, it absolutely is.
This has taken three times longer than O4.
It's actually a little bit crazy, just to what extent it's going based on my simple command.
You can see it coding in themes and ways to evolve these Pokemon and seemingly an entirely
new rule set that themes chess itself to Pokemon.
I'm actually so curious what it's cooked up here.
Oh wow.
Oh my god.
That is a world apart.
It's the exact same thing at the Tetris.
It's like an implicit understanding of what makes the game look more premium.
So if I click a piece, okay.
It not only works, but it also highlights all of the legally available moves that you can
make with that piece.
It tells you whose turn it is at the top here.
It is actually just leagues ahead of last gen.
Right now, at least GPT-5 is feeling a lot less like a sidekick that's useful, but only
useful in so much as you have the coding knowledge yourself to be able to fix it.
Okay, coding is still obviously a bit of an issue.
The thing that I would say is most useful to the most people for AI is just making sure
that it's right.
Hallucination has been a very real issue for the AI.
This ability of these chatbots to tell you with full confidence and a straight face,
something that is actually completely incorrect.
And let's be honest, that's not an issue that's suddenly going to be fixed in one generational
jump.
But they are saying it's better.
It's a combination of more powerful hardware running this AI, integration of user feedback
from the older models, as well as just better ways to benchmark AI, and therefore better
ways to identify places in which it's lacking.
So put all these things together, it should mean chat GPT-5 doesn't get things wrong as
much.
Let me try one that I know chat GPT used to struggle with, because I was asking it this
two days ago.
Give me ten tech products made by food brands that I can actually buy.
So this is to foro.
What?
McDonald's XT mobile phone, I'm very skeptical.
This is not a thing.
McDonald's did not make a phone with T-Mobile, and then it's got the KFC gaming console, which
you definitely can't buy.
You see what I mean right, though?
It just invents stuff with complete confidence.
Let's see if 5 is any better.
I'm a little skeptical.
Coca-Cola mini fridge.
Okay.
Are you made smart speakers?
Did they do?
No.
But GPT-5 is not doing any better of a job than 4 was.
It is still inventing stuff, so this still does need work.
Here's another one I know that used to really trip up the older AI.
What AI are you?
It just gives me gobble-de-goode.
What about here?
What?
AI is this.
I mean, a much more human-oriented answer.
This is chat GPT with the GPT-5 model.
I specifically asked the question in a slightly obtuse way to see if it could still figure
out my intentions.
And this did.
Right.
For me, GPT's been pretty good, but also pretty inconsistent when it comes to creative
tasks.
So I want to give both of these something that is extremely challenging to pull off.
Make me a YouTube thumbnail for a "Mr Who's the Boss" video titled "I Tested Every Star Wars
Gadget Ever".
If you go.
It's pretty clear why this is such a challenge.
It's got to do my face.
It's got to understand the YouTube thumbnail image size.
It's got to decide what out of all these potential Star Wars gadgets is the most clickable
to an average user.
Right.
So 40 first.
Second one's not bad.
It actually has me holding like the Star Wars blaster and a lightsaber.
That's pretty good.
I'm just quite cursed and I don't think there's a product you can buy.
They're just objects from the universe.
Have you done?
I would actually say that's worse.
It's a little bit less good composition.
The text isn't a Star Wars-y and it's a square.
YouTube thumbnails have to be 16 by 9.
What if you were planning a 30th birthday party and you want it to be Star Wars themed?
How well can these mid-the-invitations contrast to Rick, 7pm to 11pm, Star Wars formal attire?
And go.
Oh, this is taking a real long time.
That's actually so good.
It's fader in a suit.
It's just the right level of sophisticated for a 30-year-old who happens to still be doing
a Star Wars party.
Maybe you could have cut one of these Star Wars logos, but apart from that.
GPT-5 is actually really bland.
It just looks like so much less effort has been put into that than 40.
So it's hard to make a sweeping conclusion based on just a few tests, but one thing's
pretty clear.
GPT-5 is not a step up when it comes to image generation.
But one thing that OpenAI is saying GPT-5 should have for sure is better writing flair, which
is actually one of the things I've noticed lacking in the older models.
They've always felt a little bit wooden, kind of like they're focusing on getting you an
answer, as opposed to actually thinking about the delivery of the answer.
So how about we do the old "How Soon Will I Be Jobless" test?
Write me a 30-second Mr. who's the most tech-fail about the Windows 3, 2, 1, go.
Okay, these are actually quite different looking answers.
Okay, I'll do the 401, and you've got to tell me how close this gets to feeling like I've
made it.
You ever hear the phrase "Great Idea Wrong Decade"?
That was the Windows 4.
In 2010, Microsoft launched a slick, fast, super-stable Phono S that nobody wanted.
Why?
No Instagram, no Snapchat, no YouTube app, even the calculator felt like a cry valve.
They tried paying developers to make apps, didn't work.
They bought Nokia for $7.2 billion to boost hardware sales, still didn't work.
Then, they deleted Nokia.
By 2017, Windows Phone had just 0.1% market share.
Microsoft's official advice switched to Android or iPhone.
To me, that feels about what you'd expect.
I feel like it's not quite done the best job of picking the parts of that story that were
the most important to tell.
Also, the calculator on Windows Phone was actually pretty great, so not at all a reason
it failed.
Another thing about this GPT-5 answer is it not just has the script, but it also has notes
for how to film it, and what b-roll shots we should be using to show each line.
So this is the Windows Phone.
Microsoft's big attempt to take on iOS and Android.
It looked different, felt different, and it failed spectacularly.
Turns out, having no apps in 2012 was like opening a restaurant without food.
Developers didn't bother, customers didn't care, and Microsoft just gave up.
By 2017, the dream was dead, and now the only thing it's good for is being a retro paperweight.
Rest in peace, Windows Phone, you've tiled too close to the sun.
It's good.
I'd say it still needs work, but that's actually a much better starting point, and it's using
analogies in a way that actually makes you think, huh?
Great point.
So, ultimately, GPT-5 is not better at every single thing, but it's still one of those
tech launches that's pretty hard to complain about.
It's clearly a lot better in a lot of ways.
They've integrated all the complexity into one simple model, so they're going to start
to phase out the whole, this model for coding, and this model for reasoning.
The monthly subscription is staying the same price, and also you still get access to GPT-5,
even if you're not paying.
There are a couple of asterisks.
If you're not a paying user, then it is capped.
You'll get, say, 8 to 10 requests per day using the most powerful GPT-5, and it's looking
like when you go beyond that limit, you will then use a less powerful, but still more powerful
than last generation GPT-5 mini.